# FELIPE TAHA SANT'ANA, Ph.D.

+48-882-844-704 | ftahas@proton.me | ftahas.github.io

in ftsantana | 🕥 ftahas | 🎔 ftsantan | 📵 ORCID | 🗲 Scholar

## Introduction

I am a scientist with an interdisciplinary background on theoretical physics, electrical engineering, and computer science. During my undergraduate studies, I worked on numerical techniques for astroparticle physics problems. Then, I started working on AI applied to autonomous robots until I finished my M.Sc. diploma on the field. Since then, during my Ph.D. in theoretical physics and in my postdoc positions, I acquired an extensive expertise on interacting quantum systems, integrable models, quantum field theories, mathematical physics, and AMO physics in general. In addition, I have experience in the private sector, where I have worked on financial models and data science. Currently, I am a Polonez Bis fellow at the Institute of Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences, working on integrable quantum field theories in one dimension under the project CIQS: Correlation aspects of Interacting Quantum Systems in reduced dimensionality.

#### **EDUCATION**

• University of São Paulo

04/2020

Ph.D. in Physics

São Carlos, Brazil

- Keywords: Bose gases, optical lattice, quantum phase transition, 1d interacting systems.
- Thesis: A study on quantum gases: bosons in optical lattices and the one-dimensional interacting Bose gas. arXiv:2006.13100; teses.usp

#### • University of São Paulo

07/2015

M.Sc. in Electrical Engineering

São Carlos, Brazil

- Keywords: Autonomous robots, dynamical environments, collision probability estimation.
- · Dissertation: Estimação de probabilidade de colisão com obstáculos móveis para navegação autônoma. teses.usp

#### University of São Paulo

07/2012

B.Sc. in Physics

São Carlos, Brazil

#### EXPERIENCE

# • Institute of Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences [

11/2022 - 10/2024

Assistant Professor

Warsaw, Poland

- NCN Polonez Bis 1 Fellow
- Principal Investigator of the project CIQS: Correlation aspects of Interacting Quantum Systems in reduced dimensionality

### Faculty of Physics, University of Warsaw [ ]

10/2020 - 09/2022

Assistant Professor

Warsaw, Poland

 Postdoctoral researcher within the NCN Sonata project "Dynamic correlation functions of quantum integrable models: in and beyond the equilibrium" headed by Miłosz Panfil.

## • Institut de Physique de Nice, Universitè Côte D'Azur [�]

06/2018 - 05/2019

Ph.D. Researcher

Nice, France

• Doctoral researcher under CAPES/COFECUB bilateral collaboration.

#### • São Carlos Institute of Physics, University of São Paulo [

04/2016 - 04/2020

Ph.D. Researcher

São Carlos, Brazil

• Doctoral researcher within project "Bose gases in optical lattices" headed by F.E.A. dos Santos.

# Luz Financial Solutions [ ]

São Carlos, Brazil

Financial Analyst

03/2013-07/2015

• São Carlos School of Engineering [ M.Sc. Researcher

São Carlos, Brazil

• Master student within the project "Dynamic environments in autonomous robotics" headed by Valdir Grassi Jr.

#### Warthog Robotics [ ]

2012-2013

AI Developer

São Carlos, Brazil

#### **TEACHING**

Quantum Field Theory

 Institute of Physics, Polish Academy of Sciences
 Lecture notes

 Statistical Physics

 Faculty of Physics, University of Warsaw
 Quantum Mechanics
 Faculty of Physics, University of Warsaw
 Warsaw, Poland

 Quantum Mechanics

 Faculty of Physics, University of Warsaw
 Warsaw, Poland

#### **PROJECTS**

Computational Physics

São Carlos Institute of Physics, University of São Paylo

• CIQS: Correlation aspects of Interacting Quantum Systems in reduced dimensionality November 2022 - October 2024 Keywords: Quantum Field Theories, Integrable models, 1d interacting systems

 Project No. 2021/43/P/ST2/02904 co-funded by the National Science Centre and the European Union Framework Programme for Research and Innovation Horizon 2020 under the Marie Skłodowska-Curie grant agreement no. 945339.

## **PUBLICATIONS**

C=CONFERENCE, J=JOURNAL, P=PATENT, S=IN SUBMISSION, T=THESIS

2017

São Carlos, Brazil

- [J.1] Oleksandr Gamayun, Miłosz Panfil, Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, Kubo-Martin-Schwinger relation for an interacting mobile impurity, Phys. Rev. Research 5, 043265, 2023. arXiv:2308.06482
- [J.2] Oleksandr Gamayun, Miłosz Panfil, Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, Mobile impurity in a one-dimensional gas at finite temperatures, Phys. Rev. A 106, 023305, 2022. arXiv:2202.07657
- [J.3] Miłosz Panfil, Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, The relevant excitations for the one-body function in the Lieb-Liniger model, J. Stat. Mech. (2021) 073103. arXiv:2104.10491
- [T.1] Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, A study on quantum gases: bosons in optical lattices and the one-dimensional interacting Bose gas, University of São Paulo thesis repository arXiv:2006.13100
- [J.4] F. T. Sant'Ana, F. Hébert, V. Rousseau, M. Albert, P. Vignolo, Scaling properties of Tan's contact: Embedding pairs and correlation effect in the Tonks-Girardeau limit, *Phys. Rev. A* **100**, 063608 (2019). arXiv:1908.08714
- [J.5] Felipe Taha Sant'Ana, Axel Pelster, and Francisco Ednilson Alves dos Santos, Finite-temperature degenerate pergutbation theory for bosons in optical lattices, *Phys. Rev. A* **100**, 043609 (2019). arXiv:1906.09661
- [J.6] M. Kübler, F. T. Sant'Ana, F. E. A. dos Santos, and A. Pelster, Improving mean-field theory for bosons in optical lattices via degenerate perturbation theory, *Phys. Rev. A* **99**, 063603 (2019).arXiv:1804.08689
- [C.1] Felipe Taha Sant' Ana et al., Warthog Robotics Team Description Paper 2012, Latin American Robotics Competition Symposium (2012).

## TALKS AND POSTERS

Correlation aspects of interacting quantum systems in one dimension	10-14 July 2023
International Conference on Statistical Physics - SIGMAPHI 2023, Chania, Greece	
Correlation aspects of interacting quantum systems in reduced dimensionality	December 2022
BEC seminar, CFT PAN, Warsaw, Poland	
The relevant excitations for the one-body function in the Lieb-Liniger model	20/02 - 04/03, 2022
São Paulo School of Advanced Science on Quantum Fluids and Applications, São Carlos, Brazil	
Correlation features of interacting bosons	October 2021
Condensed matter physics seminar, FUW, Warsaw, Poland	
Understanding the important excitations in the Lieb-Liniger model	April 2021
Student workshop on integrability, 2021, Hannover, Germany	
• A study on quantum gases: bosons in optical lattices and the interacting Bose gas	December 2020
Condensed matter physics seminar, FUW, Warsaw, Poland	
Bosons in optical lattices	30/01 - 10/02, 2017
School on Interaction of Light with Cold Atoms, São Paulo, Brazil	

#### **SKILLS**

- **Programming Languages:** Fortran, C, C++, Python, HTML, Julia, R
- Systems and softwares: Linux, LaTeX, Mathematica, MatLab, JupyterLab, ROS
- Specialized Area: Data Science, Machine Learning
- Research Skills: Quantum Information and Computation, Quantum Field Theory, AMO Physics, Integrability, AI, Autonomous Robots
- Languages: Portuguese (Native), English (Professional Proficiency), Spanish (Intermediate), Polish (Basic)